Finding Aid for James G. O'Hara Papers 1958-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Congressional Papers
  - Democratic Party
    - O'Hara Rules Commission 1969-1972
      The Mikulski Commission was appointed by the Democratic National Committee in September 1972 to review the party's delegate selection procedure. O'Hara was not a member of the Commission but he did testify before it and followed its activities closely. In 1974 O'Hara was appointed to the Democratic Party Compliance Review Commission which was charged with enforcing the Mikulski Commission's delegate selection guidelines.
      The papers relating to these commissions and committees include staff memoranda, background and issues papers, transcripts of hearing or copies of statements made to the commissions, reports and resolutions, and correspondence with commission members, Democratic Party officials, and members of the public.
      - Formation and Organization of Commission
        - Finances (Box 44)
        - Members (Box 44)
        - Staff (Box 44)
      - Charter Proposal, 4 folders (Box 44)
      - Codification of Convention Rules (Box 44)
      - Correspondence
        - General
          - 1969 (Box 44)
          - 1970-1972 (Box 44)
        - With Members
          - 1969 (Box 44)
          - 1970-1972 (Box 44)
      - Democratic National Committee, 2 folders (Box 44)
      - Final Report, "Call to Order ... " (Box 44)
      - Hearings
        - May 17, 1969 Washington, DC, 2 folders (Box 44)
        - July 26, 1969 Washington, DC, 3 folders (Box 44)
        - September 19, 1969 Washington, DC, 2 folders (Box 44)
        - January 15, 1970 Minneapolis, MN, 2 folders (Box 44)
        - February 20, 1970 Atlanta, GA, 2 folders (Box 44)
        - April 17-18, 1970 Salt Lake City, UT, 2 folders (Box 45)
        - April 20, 1970 Oklahoma City, OK, 2 folders (Box 45)
        - May 15, 1970 Boston, MA (Box 45)
        - June 5, 1970 Detroit, MI (Box 45)
        - June 27, 1970 Los Angeles, CA (Box 45)
        - August 14, 1970 New York, NY, 2 folders (Box 45)
        - September 11, 1970 Washington, DC, 2 folders (Box 45)
        - Synopsis of Testimony (Box 45)
      - Hughes Commission (Box 45)
      - Issues
        - General (Box 45)
        - Apportionment of Delegates, 4 folders (Box 45)
        - Convention Committees (Box 45)
        - Convention Site Selection (Box 45)
        - Credentials Challenges (Box 45)
        - Press Coverage of Convention (Box 45)
        - Television Coverage of1968 Convention (Box 45)
        - Unit Rule (Box 45)
      - Issues Paper
        - "Issues and Alternatives" (Box 45)
        - Working Papers and Drafts, 3 folders (Box 45)
        - Solicitations of Views (Box 46)
        - Comments and Reviews (Box 46)
      - McGovern Commission, 3 folders (Box 46)
      - Meetings
        - October 16, 1970 (Box 46)
        - November 13-14, 1970 (Box 46)
        - January 22, 1971 (Box 46)
        - February 16, 1971 (Box 46)
        - March 26-27, 1971 (Box 46)
        - June 11, 1971 (Box 46)
        - June 29, 1971 (Box 46)
        - July 30, 1971 (Box 46)
        - November 11, 1971 (Box 46)
      - Newspaper Clippings
        - 1968-1969 (Box 46)
        - 1970 (Box 46)
        - January-May 1971 (Box 46)
        - June 1971-1972 (Box 46)
      - O'Hara Speeches (Box 46)
      - "Progress Report," March 1970 (Box 46)
      - Proposed Rules, 2 folders (Box 46)
      - State Reform Commissions, 2 folders (Box 46)
      - Democratic National Committee Chairmanship (Box 46)
    - 1972 Convention
      - Rules Committee
        - Chairmanship (Box 46)
        - Correspondence (Box 46)
        - Hearings (Box 46)
        - Hearings Transcripts
          - June 22, 1972 (Box 46)
          - June 23, 1972 (Box 46)
          - June 24, 1972 (Box 46)
        - Meetings
          - July 9, 1972 (Box 47)
          - July 11, 1972 (Box 47)
          - July 12, 1972 (Box 47)
          - July 13, 1972 (Box 47)
        - Minority Reports (Box 47)
        - Resolutions (Box 47)
        - Resolutions Rejected (Box 47)
      - Parliamentarian
        - Correspondence and clippings (Box 47)
        - "The New Democratic Manual" (Box 47)
        - Rulings (Box 47)
      - Vice-Presidential Mini-Convention August 8, 1972 (Box 47)
    - Charter Commission
      - Correspondence
        - September 1972-June 1973 (Box 47)
        - July-December 1973 (Box 47)
        - 1974 (Box 47)
      - Drafts and Background Material, 2 folders (Box 47)
      - Meetings
        - April 10-11, 1973 (Box 47)
        - July 21-23, 1973, 2 folders (Box 47)
        - November 9-12, 1973 (Box 47)
        - March 15-20, 1974 (Box 47)
        - State Conferences (Box 47)
    - Mikulski Commission, 2 folders (Box 47)
    - Compliance Review Commission
      - Correspondence
        - October 1974-April 1975 (Box 47)
        - May-September 1975 (Box 47)
      - Resolutions and Background Material, 2 folders (Box 47)
    - Commission on Selection of Vice-Presidential Candidates (Box 47)
    - Coalition for a Democratic Majority
      The papers deriving from O'Hara's role in the Coalition for a Democratic Majority are closely related to his work with the Charter Commission and the Mikulski Commission. The Coalition papers include bylaws and minutes of the organization and correspondence, memoranda, position papers, and news stories concerning the Coalition's efforts to influence the Charter Commission and opposition to the affirmative action features of the Mikulski Commission guidelines.
      - Bylaws, Minutes, etc. (Box 48)
      - Correspondence
        - November 1972-September 1973 (Box 48)
        - October 1973-November 1974 (Box 48)
      - Papers on the Party Charter (Box 48)
      - Affirmative Action and Delegate Selection (Box 48)
    - Democratic Study Group
      - General (Box 48)
      - 1966 Election, 2 folders (Box 48)
      - 1968 Election, 2 folders (Box 48)
      - Congressional Reform 1964-1968 (Box 48)
    - Democratic National Committee 1972 (Box 48)
    - Democratic National Convention Committee 1976 (Box 48)
  - Miscellaneous
    The Miscellaneous series includes a diary, April-August, 1969, in which O'Hara recorded his observations on the activities of Congress and the work of the Commission on Rules. Also included in this series are folders of O'Hara speeches from the Congressional Record, a folder of certificates and awards presented to O'Hara, invitations and thank you notes, and material relating to a John F. Kennedy Memorial sculpture in Macomb which O'Hara was instrumental in having erected.
    - Subcommittee On Administrative Law and Government Relations 1976 (Box 48)
    - Conference of Great Lakes Congressmen 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 48)
    - US-Japan Assembly 1967-1971 (Box 48)
    - O'Hara Diary April-August 1969 (Box 48)
    - Awards, Certificates, etc. (Box 48)
    - Invitations, Thank You notes, etc. (Box 48)
    - Kennedy Memorial Sculpture in Macomb (Box 48)
    - Congressional Record tear sheets, 1958-1976, 12 folders (Box 51)
    - Speeches 1973, 1975, 3 folders (Box 51)
  - Visual Materials
    The Visual Materials series consists of 1 linear foot of photographs, mainly portraits of O'Hara or pictures of political or campaign events; most are of the annual O'Hara Shamrock Ball. Included also is a film and videocassettes from the 1976 campaign.
    - Photographs
      - Budget Committee, House of Representatives (Box 49)
      - Campaign photos (most by Black Star, May 1976) (Box 49)
      - Capitol and Christmas Tree December 17, 1975 (Box 49)
      - Cocktail party (Washington) (Box 49)
      - Colleagues-Groups (Box 49)
      - Colleagues-Individuals (Box 49)
      - Colleagues-Portraits (Box 49)
      - DC Friends of O'Hara Reception 1966 (Box 49)
      - Democratic Study Group, House April 1970 (Box 49)
      - Education (Box 49)
      - Education Conference 1968 (Box 49)
      - Education and labor Committee 1976 (Box 49)
      - Family (Box 49)
      - Kennedy and Cabinet (Box 49)
      - Labor (Box 49)
      - Macomb County Officials at Washington Conference (Box 49)
      - Michigan Promotion (Box 49)
      - Municipal Officials (Box 49)
      - Groups (Box 49)
      - Hubert H. Humphrey (Box 49)
      - Johnson and Truman (Box 49)
        see also "Political Photos"
      - Municipal Officials Conference-Groups 1970 (Box 49)
      - Municipal Officials Conference-Individuals 1970 (Box 49)
      - O'Hara, James G.
        - Capitol shots (Box 49)
        - Reception (Box 49)
        - Portraits (Box 49)
        - Working (Box 49)
        - Working with staff (Box 49)
      - Political Photos-Johnson (Box 49)
      - Political Photos-miscellaneous (Box 49)
      - Public Activities
        - Addresses (Box 49)
        - Grape Festival (Box 49)
        - School Groups (Box 49)
      - Public Relations
        - Veterans Groups, Parades, etc. (Box 49)
        - Miscellaneous large groups (Box 49)
        - Miscellaneous small groups and singles (Box 49)
        - Peach Festival and Peach Queen visiting President Ford (Box 49)
      - Shamrock Ball, various dates (Box 49)
      - Veterans (Box 49)
        see also "Public Relations"
      - Watergate Tapes August 1974 (Box 49)
    - Slides
      - O'Hara in his office, before the Capitol, or as a member of the House Committee on Education and Labor, 11 2"x2" slides color (Box 49)
    - Videocassettes
      - 1976 Campaign for US Senate, 3 videotapes U-matic (Box 49)
    - Videotapes
      - 1976 Campaign for US Senate, 1 reels 2" (Box 49)
    - Motion Pictures
      - circa 1962 WJBK (Box 50)
      - circa 1964 O'Hara and Johnson, 2 reels (Box 50)
      - TV clip on Detroit Riot July 25, 1967 (Box 50)
      - Campaign for US Senate 1976 (Box 50)
      - San Diego speech (Reel 1)
        (separately located)
  - Sound recordings
    The Sound Recordings series includes radio and television ads from O'Hara's senate campaign, several speeches by O'Hara, and a speech on O'Hara's behalf by Daniel P. Moynihan.
    - Various speeches and programs (Box 50)
      (17 cassettes and 27 sound tape reels, various sizes and speeds)
- Post-Congressional Activities
  The bulk of the Post-Congressional Subgroup consists of correspondence and other files from the years 1976 to 1987 and relate to his work as a member of the Federal Minimum Wage Study Commission and his various responsibilities with the Democratic Party. O'Hara's involvement with Ted Kennedy's bid for the presidency in 1980 is especially well represented.
  - Minimum Wage Study Commission
    - Transcripts 1980-1981 (Box 52)
    - Working Papers 1980-1981, 8 folders (Box 53)
    - Conflict of Interest 1980 (Box 53)
    - Financial 1980 (Box 53)
    - Removal of Commissioners 1980 (Box 53)
    - Research Plan 1979 (Box 53)
    - Correspondence 1979-1981 (Box 53)
    - Briefing Books 1980, 2 folders (Box 53)
    - Miscellaneous 1966-1981 (Box 53)
    - Final Report 1980 (Box 53)
  - Kennedy Campaign for President 1979-1980
    - General 1979-1980 (Box 53)
    - Michigan 1980 (Box 53)
    - Pennsylvania 1980 (Box 53)
    - Indiana and Ohio 1980 (Box 53)
    - New York 1980 (Box 53)
    - California 1980 (Box 53)
    - Union Correspondence 1979-1980 (Box 53)
    - Unions and Election Law 1979-1980 (Box 53)
    - Kennedy (Ted) correspondence 1980-1981 (Box 53)
  - Personal Correspondence 1976-1980
    - Commendations From O'Hara 1977-1978 (Box 53)
    - Commendations To O'Hara 1976-1978 (Box 53)
    - Higher Education 1976-1978 (Box 53)
    - Labor 1976-1977 (Box 53)
    - Members of Congress 1976-1978 (Box 53)
    - Former O'Hara Staffers 1977-1978 (Box 53)
    - Michigan Friends 1977-1978 (Box 53)
    - General 1977-1980 (Box 53)
  - Democratic Party (general)
    - Democratic Forum 1976-1977 (Box 53)
    - Democratic Party Rules Committee 1980 (Box 53)
    - Democratic Party Rules Committee 1983-1984 (Box 53)
  - Lobbying Activities, testimony, and miscellaneous
    - Lobby Regulation Reform 1978-1979 (Box 53)
    - Subcommittee On Postsecondary Education 1980 (Box 53)
    - Congress: House Reform 1975-1978 (Box 54)
    - Federal Election Commission reports 1976-1981 (Box 54)
    - Lobby reports 1977-1981 (Box 54)
    - Service Contract Act (O'Hara testimony) 1976-1986 (Box 54)
    - Youth Sub-Minimum Wage (O'Hara testimony) 1981-1987 (Box 54)
    - Speeches 1975-1979, 3 folders (Box 54)
    - Articles 1975-1988
      - Authored by O'Hara (Box 54)
      - About O'Hara (Box 54)